Guide to the Frederick Emmons Terman Papers SC0160
Department of Special Collections and University Archives
- Direct Instruction Costs per Student Credit Hour, 1968-1969; Series VII
  Dr. Terman was always concerned with the state of engineering education in the U.S., and after his retirement in 1965, was able to pursue this interest more actively. This study, designed and carried out by him in 1968 and 1969, determined the instructional costs per student credit hour granted in the engineering schools of major colleges throughout the country. The survey also attempted to correlate these costs with the academic stature of each institution's engineering program.
  Box 1: Contains the survey questionnaires completed and returned to Terman by the participating schools, and some related Correspondence. This box is arranged alphabetically by the name of the college.
  Box 2, folders 1-3: Correspondence and list of institutions invited to participate in the survey, but either refused to participate or did not return the questionnaire.
  Box 2, folders 4-6: Correspondence requesting copies of Dr. Terman's report on the study, arranged chronologically.
  Box 2, folders 7-8: Tabulated results and working data for the study.
  Box 2, folder 9: Articles by, and correspondence with, other researchers studying engineering education costs.
  Researchers interested in engineering education should also see Series X of this collection for articles and reports on Terman's other educational studies.
  - Forms and Instructions. 1968. (Box 1, Folder I)
  - Forms and Instructions - Masters. 1968. (Box 1, Folder 2)
  - Institutional Reports. A-CL. 1968 - 69. University of Arizona; Arizona State University; Auburn University; Carnegie-Mellon Institute; Case Western Reserve; City University of New York; Cleveland State University. (Box 1, Folder 3)
  - Institutional Reports. CO-D. 1968 - 69. University of Colorado; Colorado State University; Dartmouth College; University of Delaware; University of Denver; Duke University. (Box 1, Folder 4)
  - Institutional Reports. F-J. 1968 - 69. University of Florida; Harvard University; University of Hawaii; University of Illinois; Iowa State University; Johns Hopkins University. (Box 1, Folder 5)
  - Institutional Reports. K-Mic. 1968 - 69. Kansas State University; Marquette University; University of Maryland; University of Massachusetts; Massachusetts Institute of Technology; University of Michigan; Michigan State University; Michigan Technological University. (Box 1, Folder 6)
  - Institutional Reports. Min-N. 1968 - 69. University of Minnesota; University of Missouri; Newark College of Engineering; North Carolina State University; Northwestern University; Notre Dame University. (Box 1, Folder 7)
  - Institutional Reports. O-R. 1968 - 69. University of Oklahoma; Oklahoma State University; Oregon State University; University of Pennsylvania; Pennsylvania State University; Polytechnic Institute of Brooklyn; Rennselaer Polytechnic Institute; University of Rochester; Rutgers University. (Box 1, Folder 8)
  - Institutional Reports. S-T. 1968 - 69. Southern Methodist University; State University of New York; Tennessee Technological 'University; University of Texas; Texas A and M University; Tufts University; Tulane University; Tuskeegee Institute. (Box 1, Folder 9)
  - Institutional Reports. U-Z. '1968 - 69. Utah State University; Virginia Polytechnic Institute; University of Washington; Washington University; Wayne State University; University of Wisconsin; Worcester Polytechnic Institute; Yale University; Youngstown University. (Box 1, Folder 10)
  - Invitations to participate - not followed through. 1968 - 69. (Box 2, Folder 1)
  - List of schools invited to participate. 1968. (Box 2, Folder 2)
  - Refusals to participate. 1968 - 69. (Box 2, Folder 3)
  - Requests for copies of report. Aug. 1968 - April 1969. (Box 2, Folder 4)
  - Requests for copies of report. May 1969. (Box 2, Folder 5)
  - Requests for copies of report. June 1969 - Sept. 1972. (Box 2, Folder 6)
  - Results of Study. 1969. (Box 2, Folder 7)
  - Results of Study. Data. 1969. (Box 2, Folder 8)
  - Studies of Engineering Education Costs made by other researchers. 1970 - 74. (Box 2, Folder 9)
- Speeches, 1939-1977; Series VIII
  The four boxes of this series contain drafts, notes, and occasionally transcripts of speeches given by Dr. Terman; and correspondence related to his speeches. All materials are arranged chronologically by the date of the speech. Terman spoke before both scientific and general audiences. Most of his talks for general audiences were related to the history of electronics, and stressed his influential concept of academic-industrial interaction.
  - 1939 - 41 - notes for speeches most are untitled and undated. (Box 1, Folder 1)
    - "Current trends in radio;" klystron - (speech to Stanford Associates); television, etc. (Feb. 26, 1939); Directional antennas (Oct. 13, 1939); A.I.E.E.: speech at IRE West Coast meeting - 1939 - 41.
  - 1942 - 45 (Box 1, Folder 2)
    - "Detectors, Distortionless -- and otherwise;" Report of Retiring President Frederick Emmons Terman - Presented at I.R.E. convention, Jan. 1942; Harvard Radio Research Laboratory - opening remarks, Nov. 16, 1945.
  - Speeches - 1946. (Box 1, Folder 3)
    - "Fifteen years' electronic development in five years" - NAB address, Jan. 11, 1946; "Radar and Radar Countermeasures;" Commonwealth Club, March 15, 1946. "Modern Communication and its import: The social significance of communication" - Princeton Bicentennial, Oct. 4, 1946.
  - Speeches - 1947. (Box 1, Folder 4)
    - "Youth looks to the future." Interview on Radio Station KQW, July 12, 1947; Speech to West Coast I.R.E. Convention, Sept. 1947; R & D. research panel; "Electronics: A Basic Industry 21st Regional Trust Conference of the American Bankers Association, Oct. 24, 1947; "WI'-de Band amplifiers" - Talk at Mare Island Naval Shipyards, Dec. 11, 1947.
  - Speeches - 1948 (Box 1, Folder 5)
    - "Engineering Research" - speech to Stanford Associates, March 15, 1948; short radio talk for the inauguration of station KSRB, June, 1948 undated notes: speech on W. W. II technology given at Stanford conference, 1948; Radar Countermeasures speech to-AIEE-IRE.
  - Speeches - 1949 (Box 1, Folder 6)
    - "Fundamental research in university and college laboratories..." - Northern California Research Conference, Jan. 26, 1949; Transcript of very similar speech given to Palo Alto Chamber of Commerce, Feb. 7, 1949; "Television -- one aspect of an electronic era" - speech delivered at Bond Club, Feb. 28, 1949, and at Stanford Conference, May 14, 1949; "WCEMA Talk" - June 2, 1949.
  - Speeches - 1950 - 57. (Box 1, Folder 7)
    - "Radio Club Talk" - Feb. 1, 1950; "Some considerations involved in the direction of research," - seminar at Navy Electronics Laboratory, San Diego, May 25, 1950; WCEMA Convention - 1950; Electronics in WW II - Kiwanis Club, May 31 no year, either 1950 or 51; remark at luncheon in honor of W. F. Durand, May 3, 1951; Talk at AAUP dinner meeting, May 30, 1951; "I.R.E. 'Old Timer's Talk," June 14, 1951; Electronics talk - Bohemian Grove, July 23, 1951; speech at Varian Associates, Dec. 3, 1951.
  - Speeches - 1952 - 54. (Box 1, Folder 8)
    - "Electronics in the world today," Stanford Conference, Monterey, Feb. 22, 1952; Engineering speech to Stanford Mother's Club, March 18, 1952; "Hughes" [speech at Hughes Aircraft?], June 18, 1952; Microwave Press Party, Dec. 9, 1952; address at opening of Tube Conference, June 1953; Introductory remarks at Varian Associates presentation of Five-Year Awards, June 18, 1953; "E.C.M. in W.W. II," - Sylvania Conference, Aug. 17, 1953; Remarks as M.C. at IRE function, Oct. 28, 1953; speech at San Jose State College Dedication, Feb. 25, 1954; Speech on Engineering to Stanford Alumni Conference, March 20 and 21, 1954; "Dean's Talk," Dec. 14, 1954.
  - Speeches - 1955. (Box 1, Folder 9)
    - "University Research" - Hughes, Feb. 15, 1955; speech on engineering at Stanford for Stanford Associates, at Bohemian Club, Feb. 20, 1955; speech on the importance of Bay Area in early history of electronics, WCEMA meeting, May 12, 1955; speech on electronics, L.A. Stanford Club, May 16, 1955; edited transcript of above report, prepared for publication; "General Electric Dedication," May 27, 1955; "Contractors," Aug 18, 1955; speech to Western Economics Association, Sept. 1, 1955; "New LD Engineers," Sept. 25, 1955; "Developments in Science and Technology, 1930 - 55," reunion of the class of 1930, Nov. 18, 1955; speech at dedication of Crothers Memorial Hall [no date].
  - Speeches - 1956. (Box 1, Folder 10)
    - "Contract Research," Dean's Luncheon, Jan. 10, 1956; "spivco (?) groundbreaking," Jan. 11, 1956 - [not given]; notes for speech on Stanford for Denver-Salt Lake City Group, Jan. 1956; Stanford Conference speech in Modesto [no date]; "Engineering at Stanford," Wilbur Hall, May 16, 1956; notes for panel on "Stanford's Answer to the Challenge of Education," Alumni Conference, May 19, 1956; Development of university research and industrial applications, for meeting of I.R.E. Engineering Management Group, May 21, 1956; AIEE luncheon, June 25, 1956; Electronics as "glamour field" in science, Bohemian Club, July 24, 1956; "Contractors," Aug. 27, 1956; "TAC," Aug. 29, 1956; remarks at 3rd Annual Bay Area Quality Control Conference, Sept. 14, 1956;"Electrical Engineering Curriculum in a Changing World," Meeting of American Institute of Mining, Metallurgical and Petroleum Engineers, Oct. 15, 1956 [typed copy of speech, ready for possible publication]
  - Speeches - 1957. (Box 2, Folder 1)
    - "Developments in Electronics," East Bay Stanford Men's Club, Jan. 23; "The obligations that are part of living with engineering," S. F. Engineers Week talk, Feb. 21; "The expanding field of electronics," Chicago Alumni Conference, March 9; "Some observations of engineering and scientific manpower problems in this country and Russia," E.E. seminar, April 4; talk to Stanford chapter of AAUP on university policy, April 8; "Some Observations of Engineering and Scientific Manpower Problems in this Country and Russia," (same title as April 4 speech above), AIEE San Jose section meeting, May 8; "The Expanding Field of Electronics," Stanford Alumni Conference, May 18; talk to General Electric -Math teachers group, June 23; talk about Stanford to group of student dorm resident assistants, Sept. 20; talk about field of engineering to Stanford freshman engineers, given Sept. 23, 1956 and Sept. 22, 1957; "Personal solicitation kickoff for School of Engineering," given in L.A., Oct. 1, S.F. Oct. 2; talk to Faculty Club on supply of engineers, Oct. 4; "Research Level," Board of Trustees, Oct. 17, 1956; opening remarks at Conference on Nuclear Size and Density Distribution, Stanford, Dec. 17; "Notes on CBS telephone interview," Dec. 30.
  - Speeches - 1958. (Box 2, Folder 2)
    - Panel discussion, "The Challenge of Sputniks," Tues. Evening Series, Mem. Aud., Jan. 7; same panel, same topic presented to Stanford Associates, San Francisco, Feb. 14; "The Real Meaning of Sputnik," Stanford Conference, Phoenix, Arizona, Jan. 19; "Cooperation between Industry and Education," Young Presidents' organization dinner, May 12; introductory remarks at West Coast Advanced Placement English Conference, June 26; "Some Observations on Engineering Education," Institute of Aeronautical Sciences, July 8, 1958; "Why do we do research," Stanford Business Conference, July 22; "Naval Structural Mechanics," Aug. 11; "Contractors," Aug. 12; "TAC," Aug. 14.
  - Speeches - 1959 and undated speeches from 1950's. (Box 2, Folder 3)
    - "Reflections on the Space Age," presented to Stanford Conference, Fresno, Jan. 24, and Stanford Conference, Bakersfield, Jan. 25; welcoming remarks at Mu Alpha Theta Conference, Stanford, March 14; remarks at I.R.E. National Convention on Psychology and Electronics in the Teaching-Learning System, New York, March 25; welcoming remarks, Symposium on Applied Mechanics, Sept. 9; "Stanford University and the Electronics Community," Sept. 14; "Stanford's Academic Goals and Academic Needs," Board of Trustees, Oct. 10. Undated: "Ampex is a Pioneer," "Engineers Have to be Smarter," revised version titled, "Engineering and Engineering Education in the Modern World."
  - Speeches - 1960. (Box 2, Folder 4)
    - Welcoming remarks at opening of G. E. Summer Program for High School Economics Teachers, Stanford, June 19; "Beckman," [notes], July 19; "Research in Industry and Education," July 22; Speech to Solid State Electronics Affiliates, Sept. 22; Speech to Stanford Academic Council, Sept. 30; "The Growth of Science in Industry: The Relation Between Education and Growth Industries," International Science Foundation Brainpower Forum, Monterey, Oct. 4; "Stanford Yesterday and Today," Stanford Faculty Club, Oct. 7; "Engineering at Stanford," luncheon for new engineering faculty, Oct. 18; "Education and the Growth Industries," taped radio speech made for broadcast on "Engineering News Report" program, Oct. 30, 1960; remarks at meeting of ASEE Pacific Southwest Section, Dec. 28
  - Speeches - 1960 (Box 2, Folder 5)
    In a speech entitled "Education -A Basic Resource for Electronics" delivered at the Oct. 12, 1960 luncheon of the 16th National Electronics Conference held in Chicago, Dr. Terman pointed out the lack of R & D progress in Chicago area Industry, and how this was causing industry to lag seriously behind developments on both coasts. This speech caused considerable comment, both positive and negative. Folder contains typescript of the speech, copy of it as printed for distribution, correspondence, newspaper clippings, and notes related to speech.
    - Chicago Speech, Oct. 12, 1960.
  - Speeches - 1961. (Box 2, Folder 6)
    - Notes - TAC - Washington, March 24; "Higher Education and Training in a Research Community," Symposium on Research and the Community, New York, May 1; "Growth Industries and Education," Investment Bankers' Association Conference, Santa Barbara, June 20; remarks at Solid State Device Research Conference, Stanford, June 26; remarks introducing Dr. Killian, former President of MIT at Stanford Cubberley Conference on Education, July 27; welcoming remarks, Guidance Conference of American Rocket Society, Aug. 8; remarks at TAC and Contractors meetings, Aug. 11, 13, 15, 16, 17, 18; speech at Fairfield Semiconductor groundbreaking, Sept. 28.
  - Speeches - 1961. (Box 2, Folder 7)
    - Chicago Speech, Oct. 11, 1961. One year after his Oct. 12, 1960, Chicago speech (see folder 5), Dr. Terman spoke again at the National Electronics Conference in Chicago and evaluated the progress that had been made since his last speech. Contents include Dr. Terman's notes for his NEC panel speech, an edited, type- script version of speech "Electronics in Chicago - One Year Later," and related correspondence, criticisms, and publicity.
  - Speeches - 1962. (Box 3, Folder 1)
    - "Stanford's Needs," Los Angeles, Jan. 10; "PACE Talk," given March - April in Cleveland, Detroit, Chicago, Boston, El Paso; "Remarks made to United Kingdom Committee on Higher Education (Robbins Committee)," Bowman Alumni House, Stanford, April 17; "Engineering and Scientific Manpower for the Cold War - The Next Decade," President's Science Advisory Committee, April 21; "PSAC Panel on Scientific and Technical Manpower - Supplementary Remarks," May 8; Speech at National Academy of Sciences, April 23; "State of Science and Technology," Stanford Conference (at Stanford), May 12 -- same speech also presented at alumni conferences in Los Angeles, Orange County, New York, Washington, Monterey, Santa Barbara; "Scientificand Engineering Manpower - U.S. vs. U.S.S.R.,"Stanford Camp at Fallen Leaf Lake, Aigusc, 1967;talk at WESCON Future Engineers Luncheon, LosAngeles, Aug. 23; talk on Stanford goals in Ph.D.Research Experience for Stanford Solid StateElectronics Affiliates, Sept. 21; "PACE Address,"given in Wichita, Kansas City, St. Louis, Cincinnati,Pittsburgh, Oct. 1962.
  - Speeches - 1963. (Box 3, Folder 2)
    - Higher Education and the Federal Government,"dated March 16, 1963 (dittoed typescript - noindication that this was delivered as a speech,but was filed with speeches by Dr. Terman); "IEEE -Impossible - except for Electrical Engineers," andremarks in response to Founder's Award, both speechesdelivered at IEEE banquet, New York, March 27;introductory remarks for Dr. Piore at N.A.S., April 23:"The Need for Quality," speech at groundbreaking forScience Research Center In Dallas, May 22; "FromWireless to Radio Electronics - Glamorous All theWay," Palo Alto Rotary Club, May 27; "Thomas F.Peterson - The Man," speech dedicating the Thomas F.Peterson Engineering Laboratory at Stanford, May 31;"Engineers - Quantity or Quality?", ASME luncheon,San Mateo, Oct. 15; introductory remarks at meetingof Committee on Governmental Relations of theNational Association of College and UniversityBusiness Officers, San Francisco, Dec. 6; remarksupon receiving Wescon Award - [undated].
  - Speeches - 1963 (Box 3, Folder 3)
    - Colorado Speech - Nov. 5, 1963."The Newly Emerging Community of TechnicalScholars," 18 pp. typescript of speech presentedat the University-Industry Liaison Conference,Colorado Springs, Nov. 5, 1963. Also includedin folder are correspondence, publicity material,and programs related to this event.
  - Speeches - 1963 (Box 3, Folder 4)
    - - Manpower Speech."Scientific and Engineering Manpower in a HighlyCompetitive World," 24 pp. typescript of speechdelivered on occasions: first at WEMA Convention,Jan. 8; and secondly, at Stanford Tuesday Eveninglecture series, March 5. Also included is relatedcorrespondence and publicity material.
  - Speeches - 1964. (Box 3, Folder 5)
    - Remarks at McCullough Building groundbreaking Feb. 24; introductory remarks for Dr. Clark Millikin at NAS election, April 28; "Stanford Over the Years," Phi Beta Kappa, April 9; remarks made at dedication of White Plaza, May 23; speech accepting gift of Class of 1964 on behalf of University, June 13; remarks at Class Plate laying ceremony, June 13; commencement speech, June 14; welcoming remarks for first Carlos McClatchy lecture, Sept. 13; testimonial speech for William Gould Dow, U. of Michigan, Dec. 3.
  - Speeches - 1965. (Box 3, Folder 6)
    - Stanford Today and Tomorrow Program, Jan. 13; "The University and Technology Utilization," NASA - University Conference, Kansas City, March 3; Dr. Terman's acceptance speech for Matrix Award given by Theta Sigma Phi, May 18; response at convocation honoring Dr. Terman, May 31; "Daddario Committee," Aug. 4; "Governing the University: Administrator's Role in Building a Strong University," Society for Religion in Higher Education, Aug. 22; community dinner speech accepting City of Palo Alto's Distinguished Citizen Award, Nov. 3
  - Speeches - 1966-67. (Box 3, Folder 7)
    - Notes for remarks at IEEE Pioneer Night, Sunnyvale, April 20; remarks at SMU Distinguished Engineering Alumnus Banquet, Dallas, April 21; Stanford Alumni Conference, New York, April 28; "Education in a Planned Society [U.S.S.R.]," annual meeting of San Francisco Section of IEEE, June 15; same speech delivered at IEEE Symposium on Electromagnetic Compatibility, San Francisco, July 12; same speech at Rotary Club luncheon, July 20; welcoming remarks at NSF Summer Institute on Case Methods for Teaching Engineering, Aug. 15; observation on Engineering Education in Soviet Union, WESCON Panel on Education, Aug. 25; "SMU Foundation for Science and Engineering," Industry-Faculty luncheon, Oct. 6; opening remarks at Joint URSI/G-AP Technical Session, Dec. 7, 1966. 1967: Opening remarks, NSF Summer Institute on Case Methods in Engineering, Aug. 21, 1967; speech at dedication of University of South Carolina Science Building, Oct. 21, 1967.
  - Speeches - 1968. (Box 3, Folder 8)
    - SCAS speech, Jan. 24; SCAS Panel, April 30; Farmer's Investment Club, May 8; "Development of an Engineering College Program," Stanford Alumni Conference, May 18; CCHE Education Committee, May 20; SMU Foundation Board, May 22; "The Expanding Partnership between Industry and Engineering Education in the USA," Seminar on Engineering and Technology, Taiwan, June 24; "Observations on Modern Engineering Education in USA," Seminar on Modern Engineering and Technology, Taiwan, June 25; "Engineering Education as a Factor in Economic Development," Republic of China Manpower Panel, July 8; "Engineering in New York," Polytechnic Institute of Brooklyn, presentation to New York Regents, Dec. 20; speech on engineering education to ASEE, Dec. 27.
  - Speeches - 1969. (Box 4, Folder 1)
    - "A Study of Engineering Education in California," Statewide Education Committee, California State Chamber of Commerce, Jan. 21; "Cost-Size Considerations," Institute for Engineering Deans, Monterey, April 2; "General Advice to Prospective Teachers," H. H. Skilling's teaching seminar, April 17; "Supply and Demand for Engineers," ASEE - Relations with Industry Committee, May 8; remarks in response to receiving ASE Award, June 24; introduction for Dan Noble at SSE Industrial Affiliates program, Sept. 29; "Faculty- Student Relations with the Industrial Environment," National Association of State Universities and Land Grant Colleges, Nov. 11; "Plans, Programs, and Problems " Missouri Association of Colleges and Universities, Dec. 2.
  - Speeches - 1970. (Box 4, Folder 2)
    - R.R.L. Technical Program - Division 15 Reunion, March 26; "Supply of Scientific and Engineering Manpower: Shortage or Surplus?" SMU Sigma Xi Club installation, April 16; remarks upon receiving Alumni Association's Hoover Medal Award, April 29; "Engineering and Scientific Manpower," PSAC presentation, June 15; "Early Evolution of Electronic Warfare Technology," Keynote Address at Association of Old Crows Convention, Oct. 6; remarks on the presentation of "Golden Spike Awards" at the 1970 Volunteer Leadership, Conference, Oct. 9.
  - Speeches - 1971. (Box 4, Folder 3)
    - "Disparity between Educational System and the Need," remarks at E.E. class seminar at Stanford, Feb. 1; "Engineering Education in the Seventies," Engineering Dean's Institute, Austin, April 7, "Engineering is Relevant," address at U.C. Davis College of Engineering Commencement Ceremony, June 16; speech on Florida's State of Engineering Education, presented to U. of Florida Regents, Oct. 15.
  - Speeches - 1972. (Box 4, Folder 4)
    - Introduction for Joseph Petitt, Tau Beta Pi dinner, Jan. 28; remarks presenting Palo Alto Chamber of Commerce's Distinguished Citizen's Award to David Packard, Feb. 29; remarks at SMU dinner, May 15; Memorial Tribute at Service for Stephan Timoshenko, June 15; "Trends in Engineering Education in the United States," Taiwan, June 27; "Role of Advanced Graduate Training in Industrial Development," Public lecture, Seoul, Korea, Sept. 1; "Early Electronics in the West," Wescon Convention, Sept. 20.
  - Speeches - 1973. (Box 4, Folder 5)
    - "Engineering Manpower for the Future," ASEE Relations with Industry Conference, Feb. 8; "The Graduate's Place in the World," speech at Initiation Banquet of Stanford Chapter of Sigma Xi, May 21; "On Engineers and Engineering," Palo Alto Rotary Club, Nov. 12; "Bay Area Electronics -- Then and Now," speech at WEMA's 30th Anniversary Banquet.
  - Speeches - 1974. (Box 4, Folder 6)